It was a calm winter morning and the faint golden light of the sun filtered into our sitting room at Baker Street,
illuminating the quiet chaos of books, newspapers and Holmes' chemical apparatus.
I had been attempting to follow an article in the Times,
while Holmes, with his customary detachment, perused a slim monograph on rare gemstones.
Hmm, look Watson, hmm.
Here lies an instructive example, an account of a jewel thief who failed because he ignored the simplest observation.
You never cease to find lessons in these reports, Holmes,
yet what intrigues me is how you manage to reduce matters of the most bewildering complexity to mere trifles.
Elementary, my dear Watson.
A man must train his eyes to see and his mind to connect what others discard.
..
Complexity is but the mask of ignorance.
And yet, I confess, I am still struggling with that art.
Every time I attempt to emulate you, I fall into error.
That is precisely why I persist in your education, Watson.
Wysh is not contouring, it is discipline.
Now observe, your boots carry faint traces of the reddish clay from yesterday's walk by the serpentine.
You did not notice it yourself, yet it speaks clearly to me.
By Jove, Holmes, I had not the slightest notion. You astound me every time.
And so, when a true mystery presents itself,
the practice of noticing will serve us well.
..
Ah! Listen!
That is Mrs. Hudson's tread. She brings us a visitor.
A gentleman to see you, Mr. Holmes, says it's urgent.
The visitor entered, a tall naval officer with weather-beaten features and a look of suppressed anxiety.
His uniform was impeccable, yet his gloved hands trembled slightly as he removed his cap.
Mr. Holmes, Dr. Watson, forgive the intrusion.
I am Commander James M. Watson.
I am the artillery of Her Majesty's Navy.
I come on a matter of the gravest urgency concerning a jewel known as the Blue Water.
Blue Water? I have heard whispers of that name. Pray enlighten us, Commander.
The Blue Water is no ordinary jewel, gentlemen.
It is a sapphire of extraordinary size and purity, long kept as a naval trust.
Yesterday, from a locked compartment aboard my ship, it vanished.
I am ruined if it is not recovered.
..
Holmes and I were seated in a handsome cab with Commander Illery.
See, the frost of that winter morning clung to the windows as we rattled toward the docks by the Thames.
I confess, my imagination was fired by the prospect.
A jewel of incalculable worth, a theft upon a naval vessel, and Holmes in his element.
..
Gentlemen, this is the Dauntless, my ship, and the scene of this deplorable theft.
Remarkable, Holmes!
The sheer order of a naval deck, yet within such order, a crime of the first magnitude.
Okay, and that, Watson, is the paradox which interests me.
A theft amidst perfect vigilance suggests either extraordinary cunning or internal collusion.
I fear as much. The Blue Water was kept in the Captain's cabin, in a steel box with double locks.
Only I and the First Lieutenant had keys. Yet the box was found forced open this morning.
But surely, Holmes, that suggests a most limited field of suspects.
Commander Illery ushered us below deck, into the Captain's quarters, where the theft had occurred.
The cabin was orderly, almost austere, yet its every detail invited scrutiny under Holmes' searching gaze.
A crude instrument used, and in haste, this was no professional cracksman.
Note the rough scoring here, Watson, and the fragment of metal still lodged in the keyhole.
By heavens, Holmes, you perceive all this from a mere glance.
A not a glance, Watson, an accumulation of small certainties.
Observe the dust displaced on the carpet, scarcely disturbed elsewhere, but heavily pressed here.
Someone note to ply his tool.
Then the thief must have acted in the night, when silence covered his efforts.
Just so. Yet why here, and why now? That is what we must uncover.
Commander, who had access to this cabin?
Only myself, the first lieutenant, and occasionally the ship's steward when bringing supplies.
No one else would dare.
Commander Illery, pained with strain, wasted no time in summoning the two men under suspicion,
Lieutenant Graves, his second-in-command, and the ship's steward, Mr. Finch.
Holmes suggested that the mess hall would provide sufficient space and privacy for the examination.
With measured dread, we made our way along the polished corridors of the vessel until we emerged into that long chamber
where officers took their meals.
Mr. Holmes, this is Lieutenant Graves, and here, Steward Finch, gentlemen, you will answer Mr. Mr.
Holmes, directly and fully.
Please be seated. I am less concerned with rank than with truths.
..
Narrating, I noted the contrast. The lieutenant, with an officer's stiff bearing and narrowed eyes,
and the steward, pale, twitching, visibly ill at ease, hums, with his piercing gaze,
seemed to weigh both men as one might examine specimens in a cabinet.
Lieutenant Graves, let us begin. At what hour did you last see the jewels secure in the captain's safe?
Shortly after the evening round, sir. I verified the locks myself at half-past nine. The safe was undisturbed. Ah!
...
Steward Finch, when were you last in the cabin?
I? I brought wine for the captain's table at supper, sir. That was all. I never touched the safe.
The man seemed shaken.
Though whether from guilt or fear of authority, I could not tell.
Tell me, Finch, why do your boots bear traces of reddish clay, when we stand upon damp cobble and salt-stained planks?
I went ashore yesterday, sir. Only briefly.
Briefly? And yet the clay clings thickly. Not the trace of a fleeting step, but the imprint of a prolonged errand. Where precisely did you go?
To, to fetch tobacco, sir.
Near Coving Garden.
And you, Lieutenant? Did you observe Finch absent from the ship yesterday?
No, sir. To my knowledge, he never left.
That's false. I went ashore. I swear it.
..
Enough. The contradiction itself is valuable. Watson, note how truth resists alignment. The clay upon Finch's boots, the denial of Graves.
One of them conceals more than he admits.
The interrogation aboard the Dauntless left my mind in turmoil. Finch's trembling denials, the Lieutenant's stiff refusals, and Holmes's quiet absorption all seemed to form pieces of a puzzle whose outline I could barely perceive.
When, late in the afternoon, Holmes suddenly declared that we must return ashore at once, I pressed him for an explanation. But he offered only that enigmatic smile which told me nothing and promised everything.
Habs, may I not at least know where we hasten?
Patience, Watson. The clay upon Finch's boots was not of Coving Garden, nor of the Thames docks. It was from a garden soil unique to this quarter, red with iron. A careless slip betrayed him.
Then you believe Finch lied about his errand?
We entered the dim stairwell of the Nodging House.
You really we?
The air smelled of boiled cabbage and damp plaster, while the groan of old boards echoed beneath our seats.
We walked down the steps. Holmes, with noiseless tread, led us upward until we reached a door faintly marked with the Steward's name.
Ha! ha! Here lies the heart of our matter. Observe, Watson, the wooden box locked yet light in the hand.
Could it contain the blue water itself?
Not so heavy, nor merely papers, perhaps correspondence. Yet even scraps of ink may speak louder than gems.
Here, letters in a foreign language.
The hand of the Lord.
Italian. And see, this seal of a pawnbroker in Clerkenwell. The Steward was entangled in debt.
Debt! Then perhaps he stole the gem to settle his obligations.
Too crude for that. The forced lock. The clumsy entry. These do not speak of a desperate debtor. They speak of a decoy. The true hand is more disciplined.
Then you believe Finch is but a pawn?
That very evening, Holmes led us to Clerkenwell, where gas lamps glowed feebly upon shuttered shops.
At the corner stood the pawnbroker's establishment, mentioned in Finch's papers. Holmes, with quiet instructions, stationed us in shadow while he himself vanished inside.
Narrating, the minutes dragged. I felt my pulse quicken with every passing sound, until at last the shop-door creaked and a tall figure in naval greatcoat slipped within. Holmes's snare was closing.
Graves, by heaven, it is he!
In all the adventures I shared with my friend Mr. Sherlock Holmes, few rivaled the tension of that fog-drenched night in Clerkenwell when Lieutenant Graves slipped into the pawnbroker's shop.
Bearing that fateful parcel, I felt the very air quiver with the weight of justice about to descend.
Watson, observe! The parcel's bulk, its manner of unfolding. Yes, there! The blue water gleams at last!
By heavens, it is the sapphire!
Now, Commander, your moment!
I will confront your lieutenant and reclaim your honour!
Graves, you vile traitor! You dared betray the trust of the navy!
Ay, I only meant to hold it as collateral. The debts, my honour, was lost already.
Hours later, safe within the familiar warmth of Baker Street, I pressed Holmes for a full account. The fire crackled in the grade, and the sapphire itself lay upon the table, casting a faint blue radiance, as if mocking the fog and shadows of the night's adventure.
Holmes, you must explain how you unravelled the tangle so swiftly.
It was all, my dear Watson, a matter of exclusion. The lock upon the safe was forced with crude haste, clearly to suggest a common thief. Yet Graves possessed both the knowledge and the opportunity. He contrived to leave false traces, and seized upon Finch's debts to deflect suspicion.
The red clay was the pivot.
Finch, indeed, bore it upon his boots. But it was not from Govent Garden, as he claimed. It belonged to the very street where he lodged.
Why, he lodged! The act, coupled with Graves's denial of Finch's absence, revealed collusion of silence and deceit.
Then Finch was guilty of weakness, not of theft?
..
Precisely. Graves preyed upon Finch's desperation, using his room and debts as camouflage.
Yet the lieutenant's own arrogance led him to the pawnbroker, where his hands betrayed him with the sapphire itself.
And so the Bluewater is safe again, thanks to your science of deduction.
.